Hi everybody!
Valentin is my name
I'm a programmer like every speaker here
Programmer means write code for money
Well, not exactly
And not always
Who can tell right now what is programming for?
*(crowd) make life easier
what-what?
Make life easier, anybody else?
*(crowd) make sites
Aha
*(crowd) make money, write soft
All correct, all correct
*(crowd) to not go out and make money
Plain amazing, yeah
Well, all of you are right
Programming indeed makes life easier
Programming is fun
It is easy
with a fine print
Actually, easier than you think right now
Won't talk long
About my story
Sad story of my life
Let me show you something
Supposedly funny
Programming indeed makes life easier
Aaand with it's help you can
Do something really fast
And very helpful
Who know what imdb is?
Yes
*(crowd) It's ratings
It's movies database like kinopoisk but in English
*(kinopoisk is Russian imdb)
Big one, imdb.com
And they dump all info to the text files on their site which can be downloaded
Huge file with the size of 0.5GB
With all titles, release dates
And ratings, most interesting
So
Let's write a program
Which will help to pick something new to watch
To begin, everybody is able to see? Shoud I make it bigger?
*(crowd) Bigger is better
Bigger like this, is it better?
*(crowd) A little more please
Yes, sure, sure, anything
Like this
Aha
So, two files
From imdb are interesting for us
And this is how looks one of them
Pay attention
Columns at the top
Do you all know about Excel?
This is an Excel file in a nutshell, but raw
Every column
Is separated from each other with a tab symbol
Here, at the top
Headers
What do we have, a title
is for adults or no
release date
Genres
And then the rows
First movie, second movie, third movie
Fourth movie, fifth etc
And the second file
Where the first column is
First column is the same as in first file
And the second column is a rating on the site
It's the same one as in kinopoisk
Everybody know what kinopoisk is?
So, this is the same as kinopoisk rating
And the number of votes
To know if anybody is interested in the movie
What do we do with them
We'll take both of these files
And we'll try to merge them
By the first column to get whole pucture of all ratings
First, pay attention to te botton
Where's the mouse, here, this number
This is an amount of imdb movies with any rating
I'll write simple Python programm, nevermind if you don't understand something
The purpose is to show you that it's easy and fun
Supposedly
Aaaam
And we'll start with
The use of one of the Python's libraries
Which helps
To read files in such format in convenient way
Second, we have to open these files
In Python we open files with "open" function
Is here anybody who never wrote any code?
Everybody wrote something, like with Pascal in school, right?
Good, great
I'll show you now
*(mumbling) hippie-expand
Well
Yes
We open the file in "read mode"
Call it "f1"
And put file contents in the variable
Which we call "title"
For this we wrap it into the thing we just imported
Pass the file there
Aaand
The "delimiter" param which means that
backwards slash means tab symbol, it's represented that way
Each column is separated by the tab symbol
And while first file is opened, we open the second one
Aaa, which is called "ratings"
It's opened in the "read" mode as well, read, the read
And we put its contents
in the
variable called "rating"
"f2"
delimiter is equals
the tab symbol as well
Remember what's next?
We take the ratings file
We begin to go through each line and try to merge it with a row from the first file
Problem is - the first file is much bigger than the second one
It's about 5 million lines because not every movie has a rating
That's why
Everybody is familiar with a loop concept?
Yes? Good
This is a loop
Over each row from the ratings file
So, we take
The row from ratings file
Then take the row from the file with
the titles, the names
While
Aaa
The first column which is called "tconst"
is not equal to the same row
from the ratings file
We take the next
Row from the big file
You get what's happening, right?
And when they match
When they match we break out of while
By the way you see that I insert 4 spaces before each line?
It's just like begin/end in the Pascal in a nutshell
Beginning and the end of the block
I think, never wrote anything in Pascal to be honest
Ahahah
When they mached
We, uhh
Let's create an empty variable which we'll call "movies"
"Movies"
It's just a list which we'll fill with
movies in convenient format
And Python list has an "append" function
In which we'll put it in a convenient way
Aaa, movies has a title which we get from the big file
Aaaa, I think it's name is
It's name is "primaryTitle", yeah
Primary Title
*(savage English) Pri-ma-ry
Title
Release year
Which is called "start"
"Year"
Next we have genres
Which called "genres"
And the "rating" in which we're interested
We take rating from the small file, by which we
By which we go through
It's called
average rating
But we need it in the number format
Who knows the difference between int and float?
Int is a whole number, float is a number with a dot, with a comma
Like this, a fractional number
Aand, we need a number of votes
Which we also take from the small file
But we cast it to the int number
And its name is
Its name is "numVotes"
Let's cross our fingers and try to run it
I opened to the near
The console of the Python language
In which we will play
Run something
Everything is wrong because I mistyped semicolon and a colon
Let's try one more time
It seems that something is working there
We should get
movies
here
While it's counting, files are huge, let's talk about
Socializing
The biggest mistake beginner programmer could make
Is a lock in the mum's basement only with books and speak to nobody
That's why socialization is very important
Without it you'll lose the interest in what you're doing really fast
Main question which should bother you
Is where to go after this conferens
Where to hang out?
Remember first link, it's a
Telegram group
Who doesn't have Telegram - install it
*(crowd) Untill it's not blocked yet
Yes, untill it's not blocked yet
And start from there
Second link is a StackOverflow site
There you can ask your questions
It has a Russian version, English is not required
And Discord
It's for gamers, but there are programmers as well
And slack.com
It has a lot of communities as well
It's main starting points
Where to learn programming?
Probably, you started to suspect on your computer classes that
Your teachers
Have not the most up to date knowledge
Did anybody noticed it?
Yeah, yeah, good
So, the best
Learging source is the Internet
In particular
Sites, blogs
Educational videos etc
And local meetups just like this one
While we're chit-chatting here
There is something interesting over there
Yup
And the main thing is when you write code - don't keep it within
You need it to
Show it to everybody
Who has an Instagram?
Why nobody has it?
Well, github.com
is an Instagram for programmers
Where we show not our suntanned bodies but our code
Here
Let's check how it's going
Oh, look, 820200 movies
Just about like it's in the ratings file
Let's play with them a little bit
So, Python has a module which is called "random"
It's to work with random things
So, let's look
For random
"choice" which is choice in English
Some random movie
Ahhh
Don't concentrate to much on this one
Movie among the movies
if
Its rating
Ra-ting
Yeah, bigger...
Let's take 8.5
And
And, for example, votes are
more that 10000
We don't want some unknown
shit to wach
And
And let's say it should be science fiction
Sci-Fi
Among its
Genres
Aha, what it suggests us to watch?
It suggest us "Inception" from 2010
Let's look for something else
*(savage English)"Mystery Science Theater 3000"
Anybody saw this?
Ahahah
Aaaa, ha-ha-ha
Let's for example
year, right?
Is more than 2010
Here's something fresher, right?
Hated in the Nation, [then same but in Russian]
Let's for example
Check out some "Action" movie
Vikings from 2013
It's alright
Or Mass Effect 3, it seems that imdb has games as well
So, programm is working
And, note that
If I, of course,
Can type today
Please
The whole program takes
20 lines of code
21 including all these things, and if we cut them
19, 18 lines of code
Just with 18 lines of code we wrote something helpful
Which you can even use
So, it was my talk purpose
You don't have to think that programming is hard
It's hard of course, but not when you just starting
All I just wrote and these slides are on github
As I said, in the Instagram for programmers
Leave a like :)
I also insist
on you to register there
And start to share your code even if it's just hello world
Or some unfinished drafts
Upload, share, nothing wrong about it
It's like shot your food and upload it to the Instagram
My twitter nickname
And in
Telegram
And in GitHub
Look for me, write me
Don't hesitate
Aa, that's all my slides, I'll open "where to hang out" slide just in case
So you write it down
That's all I have, I tried to make it fast
Ask your questions if you have any
I hope some of you is interested in trying things out
After all of this
After all of it
*(crowd) make adults!
Whaaa?
*(crowd)is adults!
Wat?
*(crowd) adult movies!
Oohh, adult movies
Let's check them out, we have time
Ha-ha
So
I didn't copy it
Let's copy it, why not, on the go
For adults
he-he
Uuumm
Here
Here we'll open our Pythony
Now it'll
It'll calculate
I wonder if imbd has adult movies ratings
I think it's any 18+ movies
So, let's check, right?
Uuumm
We'll cut the year
And instead
Rigth? Adult movies
Aaand, I forgot to close it
RIght?
Hey, stop
It turns out that there is no
for ad... Let's do it this way
Aha
"Cannot choose from an empty sequence"
It seems that there is nothing with this rating among adult movies
Let's better
Cut 10000 votes
Oh!
Kill Thrill from 2006
Some drama
Let's look for something else
Write them down, yeah, ha-ha-ha
That's it?
Laura
Crotch
Tomb Raider
*(crowd)he-he-he-he
Ok, that's enough, ha-ha-ha
So, that's it
That's all I have, he-he
Ask your questions if you have any